<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Generated by Site-Server v@build.version@ (http://www.squarespace.com) on Thu, 20 Nov 2025 14:20:45 GMT
--><rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:media="http://www.rssboard.org/media-rss" version="2.0"><channel><title>The Tunbridge Wells Psychologist | Private Clinical Psychology Therapy</title><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/</link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 15:30:22 +0000</lastBuildDate><language>en-GB</language><generator>Site-Server v@build.version@ (http://www.squarespace.com)</generator><description><![CDATA[]]></description><item><title>Living with Uncertainty After Cancer: Learning to Feel Safe When the Future Is Unclear</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/living-with-uncertainty-after-cancer-learning-to-feel-safe-when-the-future-is-unclear</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:6908e8685e950e69895f1fae</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>One of the hardest parts of life after cancer is uncertainty. Even when treatment ends or scans are clear, many people describe feeling unable to relax fully. The mind continues to ask, “What if it comes back?” or “What happens next time?” Living with uncertainty can make it difficult to plan for the future or feel present in the moment. Yet, with the right support, it is possible to live meaningfully even without absolute reassurance.</P2>

<H3>Why uncertainty feels so uncomfortable</H3> <P2>Human beings are wired to seek safety and predictability. Cancer disrupts that sense of control. Even after treatment, the body remembers the shock of diagnosis, the medical routines, and the waiting. The brain, designed to protect you, stays alert for danger. This can show up as scanning for symptoms, feeling tense before check-ups, or struggling to believe good news. Understanding that this is your mind’s attempt to keep you safe can help you respond with compassion instead of frustration.</P2> <H3>Feeling as though you’re always braced for something to go wrong</H3> <P2>Living with uncertainty often feels like holding your breath. Some days you might feel calm and hopeful, and others overwhelmed by fear. This fluctuation is normal. Many people try to push away anxiety or search for reassurance, but these strategies can backfire, keeping the mind stuck in a cycle of checking and doubt. Therapy can help you learn to live alongside uncertainty without letting it control you. Acceptance does not mean liking uncertainty, but learning how to make space for it while continuing to live a valued life.</P2> <H3>Therapeutic approaches that help</H3> <P2>Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT) offers practical ways to manage uncertainty. It teaches skills for observing anxious thoughts rather than being pulled into them and focusing instead on actions that reflect your values. For example, you might notice the thought, “I can’t plan a holiday in case I’m ill again,” and choose to plan it anyway, accepting that uncertainty is part of life. Compassion-focused therapy helps by soothing the fear system, offering kindness rather than criticism when anxiety appears. Together, these approaches help you feel safer even when you cannot be certain.</P2> <H3>Grounding in the present</H3> <P2>Uncertainty pulls the mind into the future, so grounding techniques that anchor you in the present can be powerful. You might notice the feeling of your feet on the floor, take a few steady breaths, or name five things you can see. These simple actions remind your nervous system that you are safe in this moment. Over time, grounding can help reduce the intensity of anxious surges and bring more calm to your day.</P2> <H3>Finding meaning even without guarantees</H3> <P2>One of the paradoxes of recovery is that uncertainty can also make life feel more precious. When we do not take time for granted, moments of connection and peace become more vivid. Therapy can support you in exploring what gives your life meaning now, even without certainty. This might include relationships, creativity, spirituality, or simply small daily pleasures. Focusing on meaning does not erase fear, but it can help it take up less space.</P2> <H3>Building trust in your ability to cope</H3> <P2>It can help to remember that you have already faced enormous uncertainty through treatment and recovery. Each time you have navigated fear, waited for results, or handled disappointment, you have strengthened your coping resources. Therapy helps you build on that resilience. The goal is not to eliminate uncertainty, but to feel confident that, whatever happens, you can meet it with the strength and compassion you already possess.</P2>

<P2>Uncertainty may always be part of life after cancer, but it does not have to dominate it. With understanding, mindfulness and self-kindness, you can learn to breathe again, to plan, to hope, and to live fully even in the in-between.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762191858214-X9NOWMVDHZOW3G5Z5KJZ/unsplash-image-eAkjzXCU0p0.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1004"><media:title type="plain">Living with Uncertainty After Cancer: Learning to Feel Safe When the Future Is Unclear</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>EMDR or CBT? Understanding the Differences and How to Choose</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 02:11:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/emdr-or-cbt-understanding-the-differences-and-how-to-choose</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:690a08ccad2df40932ceec13</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>When people look for therapy to help with anxiety, trauma or low mood, two names often appear: EMDR and CBT. Both are evidence-based, effective and widely used in the UK, yet they work in different ways. Understanding what each approach offers can help you decide which might suit you best.</P2>

<H3>How CBT works</H3> <P2>Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) focuses on the relationship between thoughts, emotions and behaviours. It helps you notice unhelpful thinking patterns and experiment with new responses. For example, if you tend to think “I can’t cope,” CBT might help you examine that belief, test it in small steps, and develop more balanced alternatives. It is structured, active and collaborative, with practical strategies you can use between sessions. CBT is particularly effective for anxiety, depression, phobias and panic.</P2> <H3>How EMDR works</H3> <P2>EMDR, or Eye Movement Desensitisation and Reprocessing, helps the brain process distressing memories or experiences that remain emotionally charged. During sessions, your therapist guides you to recall parts of the memory while you follow gentle eye movements or other forms of bilateral stimulation. This allows the brain to integrate the memory in a healthier way, reducing emotional intensity. EMDR is best known for treating trauma, but it can also help with anxiety, health-related distress, and feelings of being stuck or on edge.</P2> <H3>The key differences</H3> <ul> <li><strong>Focus:</strong> CBT works mainly with current thoughts and behaviours. EMDR works with how past experiences affect you in the present.</li> <li><strong>Talking vs processing:</strong> CBT involves structured discussion and cognitive exercises. EMDR is less verbal and relies on the brain’s natural processing mechanisms.</li> <li><strong>Homework:</strong> CBT often includes practice tasks between sessions. EMDR focuses more on in-session processing, with less formal homework.</li> <li><strong>Speed and depth:</strong> Some people notice changes quickly with EMDR, while others prefer CBT’s step-by-step structure. Both can be adapted to your pace and comfort.</li> </ul> <H3>Combining the two</H3> <P2>Many therapists integrate CBT and EMDR, especially when clients have both trauma and ongoing anxiety or depression. CBT offers skills to manage daily stress, while EMDR addresses the root causes that keep certain feelings locked in. This combination can be particularly effective in private practice, allowing therapy to remain flexible and individualised.</P2> <H3>Choosing the right fit</H3> <P2>If you prefer a structured, goal-oriented approach with clear strategies, CBT might feel right. If your distress feels rooted in past experiences or physical sensations you cannot shift, EMDR may be more suitable. It is also common to use both, either sequentially or together, depending on what feels most supportive. The most important factor is the therapeutic relationship and your sense of safety with your therapist. Together, you can decide which approach will help you move forward most effectively.</P2> <H3>Moving ahead with confidence</H3> <P2>Both CBT and EMDR are evidence-based and transformative. Whether you want to understand your patterns or process what has felt too heavy to face alone, the right therapy can help you rediscover calm, strength and choice in your life.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762265443707-2V440CJPCEG5A9YAFSM4/pexels-cottonbro-4101143+%281%29.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">EMDR or CBT? Understanding the Differences and How to Choose</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Parenting with Cancer: Helping Children Cope While Looking After Yourself</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 17:17:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/parenting-with-cancer-helping-children-cope-while-looking-after-yourself</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:6908e39fbcce8469ffa0f259</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>Parenting is demanding at the best of times. Add a cancer diagnosis, and the challenge can feel immense. Many parents describe feeling torn between managing their illness and protecting their children from worry. They may feel guilty for being less available, or uncertain about how much to share. Yet children often sense more than adults realise. Supporting them through honesty and warmth can help them feel secure even in difficult circumstances.</P2>

<H3>Children notice changes even when we do not speak about them</H3> <P2>Children are highly attuned to emotional shifts at home. If they notice stress or secrecy, they may fill the gaps with their own fears. Some worry they have done something wrong, while others imagine scenarios worse than reality. Gentle, age-appropriate honesty helps prevent this. For younger children, simple explanations like, “Mummy is poorly and the doctors are helping her get better,” can be enough. Older children may want more detail and opportunities to ask questions. The goal is not to remove all their worries but to help them feel included and safe to talk.</P2> <H3>Balancing protection and openness</H3> <P2>Parents often fear that being honest will make children more anxious, yet research shows that honesty paired with reassurance builds trust and reduces fear. You can share information gradually, checking what your child has understood and how they are feeling. It can also help to name emotions directly, such as, “I feel sad and worried too sometimes.” This models that difficult feelings can be spoken about and managed safely.</P2> <H3>When you cannot be there in the same way</H3> <P2>During treatment, fatigue or hospital visits can limit what you can do. Children may react with clinginess, anger or withdrawal. These reactions often come from fear of separation rather than rejection. Keeping routines where possible and explaining what will happen helps children feel secure. Small gestures, such as drawing together, reading a story over the phone, or leaving notes, can maintain connection even when energy is low.</P2> <H3>Looking after yourself as a parent</H3> <P2>It is common to feel guilty for needing rest or emotional space, but self-care is not neglect; it is essential. When you take time to recover physically and emotionally, you are better able to respond with patience and warmth. Therapy can help parents explore these feelings, release guilt, and develop strategies for managing family dynamics during treatment. Compassion-focused therapy is particularly supportive here, encouraging you to speak to yourself as you would to a dear friend in similar circumstances.</P2> <H3>Helping children manage their emotions</H3> <P2>Children often express anxiety through behaviour rather than words. They might act out, become quieter, or struggle with sleep. Encouraging open expression through drawing, writing or play can help. Validating their feelings (“It makes sense you feel worried”) reassures them that emotions are not dangerous. You might also create small family rituals, like a daily check-in or shared walk, that reinforce connection and normality.</P2> <H3>When to seek additional support</H3> <P2>If a child shows prolonged sadness, nightmares or withdrawal, professional support from a child therapist can be very helpful. Therapy gives children a safe space to express feelings they may withhold to protect you. It also offers you, as a parent, a space to reflect on how to balance your needs with theirs. Many families find that this shared support reduces pressure and helps everyone cope more calmly.</P2> <H3>Holding on to connection and love</H3> <P2>Even in the midst of treatment and uncertainty, connection remains at the heart of parenting. Love is communicated not only through activity but through presence, tone, and care. By being open about feelings and looking after yourself, you show your children what resilience and compassion look like in real life. They learn that even when life feels uncertain, love and honesty create a foundation strong enough to hold the whole family.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762190642577-KRR0BN73XSV7BYR2ZTU3/unsplash-image-JDqYwfKPzEs.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">Parenting with Cancer: Helping Children Cope While Looking After Yourself</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Fatigue and Identity Loss After Cancer Treatment</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 04:29:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/fatigue-and-identity-loss-after-cancer-treatment</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:6908d86ab637db715e402691</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>When treatment finishes, many people expect life to return to normal quickly. Friends and family may say things like, “You must be relieved it’s over” or “Now you can get back to normal.” Yet for many, that “normal” never fully reappears. Instead, there can be deep exhaustion that rest alone does not fix and a confusing sense of disconnection from the person you used to be. Post-treatment fatigue is both physical and emotional, and it can affect how you see yourself, your relationships and your confidence. Understanding why it happens is the first step towards recovery.</P2>

<H3>Why fatigue lingers after treatment</H3> <P2>The body has been through months of medical intervention, and it needs time to heal. Chemotherapy, radiotherapy and surgery place huge demands on energy systems. Yet the mind is also recovering from prolonged stress. During treatment, your body is flooded with adrenaline and cortisol as it copes with uncertainty and fear. When that crisis period ends, energy levels can crash. The nervous system needs time to adjust, and this can show up as brain fog, irritability and an overwhelming tiredness that feels out of proportion to what you are doing.</P2> <P2>For some people, fatigue also carries emotional weight. It can feel frustrating or guilt-inducing to be so tired when everyone else expects you to feel grateful or ready to celebrate. This mismatch between how you feel and how you are expected to feel can deepen the sense of isolation.</P2> <H3>The impact on identity</H3> <P2>Fatigue is not only about energy. It can touch every part of life, including how you see yourself. You may find you cannot return to work, social activities or hobbies in the same way as before. You might notice yourself comparing the “old me” with the “new me,” wondering whether you will ever regain that version of yourself. Therapy can help explore this shift gently, making space for grief about what has changed while also helping you reconnect with your values and sense of purpose now.</P2> <P2>Approaches such as ACT and compassion-focused therapy are especially useful here. They encourage curiosity and kindness towards the self rather than judgment. You might ask, “What matters most to me now?” rather than “How do I get back to who I was?” This subtle shift helps recovery feel more grounded and less pressured.</P2> <H3>Managing fatigue day to day</H3> <P2>Small, structured changes can make a real difference. Some useful strategies include:</P2> <ul> <li><strong>Pacing your energy.</strong> Balance activity with rest rather than pushing through exhaustion. Try to spread tasks across the week and plan recovery time after demanding days.</li> <li><strong>Gentle movement.</strong> Short walks, stretching or breathing exercises can support both body and mind. Movement helps regulate energy rather than drain it.</li> <li><strong>Managing expectations.</strong> Communicate with others about what you can realistically do. It is fine to say no or to cancel plans when you need to rest.</li> <li><strong>Mindful pauses.</strong> When frustration arises, take a slow breath and acknowledge, “This is hard, and I’m doing my best.” Self-compassion reduces inner pressure and allows rest to feel restorative rather than guilty.</li> </ul> <H3>How therapy can help</H3> <P2>Therapy after cancer treatment can offer both structure and emotional understanding. A therapist can help you track patterns of energy and rest, identify unhelpful self-talk (“I should be better by now”), and support you to develop more balanced routines. Compassion-focused work can help address feelings of guilt or failure, while CBT techniques support practical coping. Over time, therapy can help you move from frustration and fatigue towards self-understanding and gradual re-engagement with life.</P2> <H3>Rebuilding confidence and meaning</H3> <P2>Recovery is rarely about going back; it is about finding a new version of strength that includes everything you have been through. When energy returns, even slowly, it often brings fresh clarity about what matters most. Therapy helps you recognise that this period of rest and reflection is part of healing, not a failure to move on. With compassion and patience, you can rediscover who you are now, and begin to live fully again, even if life looks different from before.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762187667721-6GZ61GT7036Y5ACZ0Y17/Patient-Fatigue.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="600" height="400"><media:title type="plain">Fatigue and Identity Loss After Cancer Treatment</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Finding Emotional Balance During Cancer Treatment: When You’re Just Trying to Get Through Each Day</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 12:45:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/finding-emotional-balance-during-cancer-treatment-when-youre-just-trying-to-get-through-each-day</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:6908bfd4d63bbe6deec93022</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>During cancer treatment, life can narrow to one simple goal: getting through each day. There can be moments of hope followed by waves of fear, gratitude mixed with exhaustion, and a sense that emotions change faster than you can keep up. Many people say they feel as though their minds and bodies are in constant survival mode, with little energy left for reflection or self-care. Yet this phase of treatment is also a time when psychological support can make a profound difference, helping you steady yourself in the midst of uncertainty and find a little more ease along the way.</P2>

<H3>Why emotions fluctuate so much during treatment</H3> <P2>It is common to feel that your emotions are unpredictable during treatment. One day you may feel determined and focused, the next you may feel flat, tearful, or irritable. This variability is not a sign of weakness. Cancer treatment places intense demands on the body and mind, and both physical side effects and medical uncertainty can amplify emotional distress. Fatigue, pain, medication effects and disrupted routines all influence mood and concentration. Psychologically, treatment can trigger fears about the future, loss of control, and a longing for life to feel normal again. Understanding that this rollercoaster is part of the process can itself bring relief, as it means you are responding in very human ways to an extraordinary situation.</P2> <H3>Regaining a sense of stability when everything feels uncertain</H3> <P2>During treatment, many people describe feeling at the mercy of hospital appointments, results and medical decisions. It can help to focus on what is within your control, however small that might seem. Establishing gentle daily rhythms such as regular meals, rest periods, short walks, or connecting with a friend creates a sense of structure that supports emotional steadiness. Even choosing what to wear to treatment or what music to listen to on the way can remind you that you still have agency.</P2> <P2>Therapeutically, grounding techniques can be valuable. These involve bringing attention back to the present moment when anxiety or overwhelm rises. This might mean slowing your breathing, naming five things you can see around you, or placing a hand over your heart and acknowledging, “This is hard, and I’m doing my best.” Such small acts of mindfulness or self-compassion signal to the nervous system that it is safe to soften, even briefly.</P2> <H3>The emotional load of “keeping strong”</H3> <P2>People going through treatment often feel pressure, from themselves or others, to stay positive. While optimism can be helpful, constant positivity can also become exhausting. It can prevent you from expressing the full range of feelings that naturally arise, such as anger, sadness or fear. Therapy offers a space where all of these emotions can be heard without judgement. Allowing yourself to express vulnerability does not mean you are giving up, it means you are processing what is happening rather than carrying it alone.</P2> <P2>Approaches such as compassion-focused therapy and Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT) can be particularly helpful here. They support you in meeting difficult feelings with understanding rather than criticism, and in connecting with your values, what truly matters to you, so you can find meaning and direction even within treatment.</P2> <H3>How therapy can support you during active treatment</H3> <P2>Therapy during cancer treatment does not necessarily involve deep exploration of the past. Often it focuses on helping you stay grounded and supported in the present. Sessions might include strategies for managing anxiety before scans, techniques for pacing and energy conservation, or ways to communicate your needs to loved ones or your medical team. If you notice distressing images or sensations linked to your diagnosis or treatment, therapies such as EMDR can gently help the body process those memories so they no longer feel overwhelming.</P2> <P2>Therapists experienced in oncology understand the unique pressures of treatment. The work is collaborative and flexible, adapting to your medical schedule and energy levels. Even short interventions can improve quality of life, reduce distress, and strengthen your ability to cope with what lies ahead.</P2> <H3>Looking after your mind as well as your body</H3> <P2>It can be easy to prioritise the physical aspects of treatment and overlook emotional wellbeing. Yet the two are deeply connected. When the mind feels calmer, the body often rests and heals more effectively. Psychological support is not about taking away difficult emotions but about helping you feel less consumed by them. Over time, many people notice they can face treatment days with more steadiness, communicate more openly, and reconnect with moments of ordinary pleasure.</P2> <P2>Small acts of self-care, such as listening to music, sitting outside for a few minutes, or simply resting without guilt, are not luxuries. They are vital tools for resilience. When you can treat yourself with kindness, even in the midst of illness, you strengthen the inner resources that help you endure and recover.</P2> <H3>Moving forward, one step at a time</H3> <P2>You do not need to face cancer treatment in silence or isolation. Psychological support can sit alongside medical care, offering you a safe space to make sense of your experiences, manage anxiety, and find ways to live meaningfully even during uncertainty. Step by step, you can build a sense of steadiness, compassion and connection that carries you through treatment.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762181108855-N5JX360CL65ELC2B8D9A/pexels-sulimansallehi-1576939.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="2250"><media:title type="plain">Finding Emotional Balance During Cancer Treatment: When You’re Just Trying to Get Through Each Day</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>What psychology offers in pain management</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 10:59:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/what-psychology-offers-in-pain-management</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:690a14db9e38b41166986fc7</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>Facing persistent pain can feel overwhelming. Whether it is pain following surgery, pain linked with a medical condition or pain that continues despite everything being done, it is more than a physical sensation. In our clinical psychology practice, we routinely support adults whose pain has become part of a wider pattern of distress, reduced activity, mood change and uncertainty. This post sets out what psychology can offer, what the evidence shows, and how referring clinicians can help clients engage with this work in partnership.</P2>

<H3>Understanding pain as more than a tissue problem</H3> <P2>Modern pain science emphasises that pain is rarely only about tissue damage. It is shaped by biological, psychological and social factors that interact over time (Bolton & Gillett, 2023, Kovačević et al., 2024). Psychological processes such as pain-related worry, beliefs that pain always equals damage, avoidance of movement, low mood and disrupted sleep all influence how persistent pain develops and continues. For clinicians, this means assessment goes beyond scans or structural labels, and includes how the person is interpreting, responding to and living with pain.</P2> <H3>What the evidence shows for psychological intervention</H3> <P2>There is a substantial and growing body of research showing that psychological therapies add meaningful value for people living with chronic pain.</P2> <ul> <li>Systematic reviews indicate that cognitive behavioural therapy, and CBT-informed multimodal programmes, can improve pain interference, disability and psychological distress in adults with chronic pain (Sanabria-Mazo et al., 2023).</li> <li>Narrative and systematic reviews highlight effective behavioural treatments for chronic low back pain, including CBT, mindfulness-based approaches and acceptance and commitment therapy, with pragmatic guidance on selecting treatments (Mauck et al., 2022).</li> <li>A randomised clinical trial of Pain Reprocessing Therapy for primary chronic back pain reported that 66 percent of participants receiving the intervention were pain-free or nearly pain-free after four weeks, with benefits largely maintained at one year (Ashar et al., 2022).</li> <li>A BMJ network meta-analysis found psychological interventions were most effective when delivered with physiotherapy care, for example structured exercise, for chronic non-specific low back pain (Ho et al., 2022).</li> </ul> <P2>Psychological approaches are not magic fixes, however they reduce distress, improve function and strengthen self-management. They work best as part of a coordinated plan across disciplines.</P2> <H3>How therapy helps - key mechanisms</H3> <P2>As clinical psychologists, we focus on how thoughts, emotions and behaviours interact with pain, then build skills that change the day-to-day experience.</P2> <ul> <li><strong>Beliefs and meaning around pain:</strong> Many people fear that pain always signals ongoing damage. Reframing this, learning that hurt does not always equal harm, can reduce fear and avoidance and support gradual re-engagement.</li> <li><strong>Catastrophising and worry:</strong> Cycles of “this will never get better” or “if I move it will get worse” are common. We help clients notice and respond to these patterns with more balanced perspectives, which reduces distress and increases confidence.</li> <li><strong>Behavioural engagement and pacing:</strong> Boom-and-bust patterns are typical. Therapy supports pacing, activity scheduling and behavioural rehearsal so clients rebuild meaningful routines at a sustainable pace.</li> <li><strong>Mood, sleep and broader wellbeing:</strong> Depression, anxiety, poor sleep and stress amplify pain interference. Addressing these domains improves resilience, mood and daily functioning.</li> <li><strong>Self-management and autonomy:</strong> Skills practice shifts the focus from what pain does to me, to what I can do despite pain. This restores choice, identity and participation.</li> </ul> <H3>What this means for referring clinicians and clients</H3> <P2>For consultants and allied health professionals, the way we frame and coordinate care matters.</P2> <ul> <li><strong>Set expectations:</strong> Explain that therapy supports living well with pain, reducing distress and improving function. It complements medical and physical treatments.</li> <li><strong>Collaborate:</strong> Psychological input sits alongside medicines, procedures and physiotherapy. It does not imply pain is all in the head, it recognises mind and body are linked.</li> <li><strong>Encourage active engagement:</strong> The best results come when clients practice skills between sessions, try behavioural experiments and track progress.</li> <li><strong>Focus on function:</strong> Agree goals such as returning to work, walking further, or reconnecting socially. Function-focused goals align with the evidence base.</li> <li><strong>Integrate and review:</strong> With consent, share updates and review outcomes across pain, activity, mood, sleep and quality of life so the whole team stays aligned.</li> </ul> <H3>Thinking ahead - what to expect and measure</H3> <P2>Monitor not only pain intensity but also interference with life, mood, sleep, activity levels and confidence to self-manage. Many meaningful gains show up in how people live with pain rather than in a single numeric score. Given generally moderate effect sizes, therapy is one important pillar in a broader plan. For many clients, changes in function, confidence and quality of life are significant and sustained.</P2> <H3>Closing thoughts</H3> <P2>Persistent pain poses biological, psychological and social challenges. Psychological therapy offers an evidence-based contribution that helps beliefs shift, reduces distress and supports a return to valued activity. We work in partnership with clients and referrers to integrate this into a coherent plan, so pain has less power over daily life.</P2> <H3><H3>References</H3>

<P2><strong>Ashar, Y. K., Gordon, A., Schubiner, H., Uipi, C., Knight, K., Anderson, Z., Carl, E., Gray, A., Kohn, N., Sistek, S., Younger, J., & Wager, T. D.</strong> (2022). Effect of pain reprocessing therapy vs placebo and usual care for patients with chronic back pain: A randomized clinical trial. <em>JAMA Psychiatry, 79</em>(1), 13-23.  
<a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapsychiatry/fullarticle/2784694" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapsychiatry/fullarticle/2784694</a>  
</P2>

<br>

<P2><strong>Bolton, D., & Gillett, G.</strong> (2023). A revitalised biopsychosocial model, core theory, research paradigms, and clinical implications. <em>Integrative Psychological and Behavioral Science, 57</em>, 1092-1112.  
<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37681273/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37681273/</a>  
<br>Open access version: <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10755226/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10755226/</a>  
</P2>

<br>

<P2><strong>Ho, E. K. Y., Ferreira, M. L., Pinheiro, M. B., Pozzobon, D., Lin, C.-W. C., Chenot, J.-F., McLachlan, A. J., Maher, C. G., & Traeger, A. C.</strong> (2022). Psychological interventions for chronic, non-specific low back pain: Systematic review with network meta-analysis. <em>BMJ, 376</em>, e067718.  
<a href="https://www.bmj.com/content/376/bmj-2021-067718" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.bmj.com/content/376/bmj-2021-067718</a>  
<br>PubMed: <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35354560/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35354560/</a>  
</P2>

<br>

<P2><strong>Mauck, M. C., Aylward, A. F., Barton, C. E., Birckhead, B., Carey, T., Dalton, D. M., Fields, A. J., Fritz, J., Hassett, A. L., Hoffmeyer, A., Jones, S. B., McLean, S. A., Mehling, W. E., O’Neill, C. W., Schneider, M. J., Williams, D. A., Zheng, P., & Wasan, A. D.</strong> (2022). Evidence-based interventions to treat chronic low back pain: Treatment selection for a personalised medicine approach. <em>Pain Reports, 7</em>(5), e1019.  
<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36203645/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36203645/</a>  
<br>Open access version: <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9529058/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9529058/</a>  
</P2>

<br>

<P2><strong>Kovačević, I., Pavić, J., Filipović, B., Ozimec Vulinec, Š., Ilić, B., & Petek, D.</strong> (2024). Integrated approach to chronic pain: The role of psychosocial factors and multidisciplinary treatment, a narrative review. <em>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 21</em>(9), 1135.  
<a href="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/21/9/1135" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/21/9/1135</a>  
<br>PubMed: <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39338018/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39338018/</a>  
</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762269462170-9JD9D6HX4MPVVR8FJE64/unsplash-image-oOW6Iju06T0.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="996"><media:title type="plain">What psychology offers in pain management</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>EMDR Therapy for Anxiety: Calming the Body When Talking Isn’t Enough</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:39:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/emdr-therapy-for-anxiety-calming-the-body-when-talking-isnt-enough</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:6908be86cc29745edc9f8221</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>When people think of EMDR therapy, they often associate it with trauma or post-traumatic stress. But EMDR can also be a powerful way to treat anxiety, especially when the body seems stuck in a state of alert even without a clear reason. Many people describe feeling constantly on edge, knowing their fear is out of proportion, yet unable to switch it off. EMDR offers a different route to calming that response, by helping the body and brain complete processes that talking alone can’t always reach.</P2>

<H3>Why anxiety sometimes doesn’t respond to reasoning</H3> <P2>When you feel anxious, your body is doing exactly what it was designed to do: detect danger and protect you. The difficulty is that the alarm system sometimes becomes over-sensitive. You might tell yourself, “There’s nothing to worry about,” yet your heart still races. Traditional talking therapies such as CBT can help you identify and challenge unhelpful thoughts, but when anxiety feels stored in the body (tight chest, shallow breathing, muscle tension) thinking alone might not fully settle the nervous system. EMDR works directly with that physical layer.</P2> <H3>How EMDR helps the body feel safe again</H3> <P2>EMDR (Eye Movement Desensitisation and Reprocessing) helps the brain reprocess distressing memories or sensations so they no longer trigger such intense reactions. During sessions, your therapist guides you to recall an image, thought or feeling linked to your anxiety, while you follow gentle bilateral stimulation such as side-to-side eye movements or alternating taps. This process activates both hemispheres of the brain, allowing stuck material to be “digested” and integrated more adaptively. Over time, situations that once felt threatening start to feel more manageable and less charged.</P2> <P2>People often notice changes not just in their thoughts but in their bodies. They might describe a sense of release, warmth or spaciousness. The body learns that it is safe again, and the anxiety system no longer needs to stay on high alert. This can be especially helpful if you have experienced prolonged stress, medical anxiety, perinatal fears, or ongoing pressure that has left your system feeling constantly vigilant.</P2> <H3>EMDR when there’s no obvious trauma</H3> <P2>Many people are surprised to find EMDR helpful even when they cannot pinpoint a specific traumatic event. The therapy is not only for major traumas but also for “little t” experiences - times when you felt powerless, overwhelmed, or unsupported. These can accumulate and teach the nervous system that the world is unsafe. EMDR helps identify and reprocess those underlying experiences so your present-day responses make more sense and feel less automatic.</P2> <P2>For example, someone with social anxiety might recall early memories of embarrassment or exclusion. Someone with health anxiety might link their fear to a past medical scare or a period of uncertainty. By working gently with these memories, EMDR can lower the intensity of current anxiety responses and free up emotional energy for living more fully.</P2> <H3>What EMDR sessions can look like</H3> <P2>EMDR sessions are structured but always collaborative. After an initial assessment, your therapist helps you build grounding and stabilisation skills so that you feel safe to process difficult material. This might include breathing exercises, visual imagery or developing a calm “safe place”. Once you have those resources in place, you begin working through the experiences or sensations that trigger anxiety, one step at a time.</P2> <P2>Each set of eye movements or taps lasts only about 30 seconds. You pause frequently to notice changes in thoughts, images or body sensations. The therapist supports you to stay present and grounded. The aim is not to erase memories but to help your brain file them correctly, so they no longer trigger alarm responses. Over sessions, people often describe feeling lighter, more settled and able to face previously difficult situations without the same intensity of fear.</P2> <H3>Integrating EMDR with other therapies</H3> <P2>In our clinic, EMDR is often integrated with approaches such as CBT, ACT and compassion-focused therapy. CBT can help you notice current patterns of avoidance or over-control; ACT supports you in living according to your values even when anxiety shows up; compassion-focused work helps soothe the inner critic that fuels worry. EMDR complements these by addressing the body-based memory networks beneath the surface. Together, they form a rounded, evidence-based approach that helps both mind and body recover their balance.</P2> <H3>When to consider EMDR for anxiety</H3> <P2>EMDR may be particularly helpful if you feel that anxiety lives in your body - persistent tension, racing heart, sudden waves of fear - or if you’ve tried other talking therapies and still feel stuck. It can also support recovery after long periods of stress, burnout, medical treatment or pregnancy-related trauma. Because EMDR focuses on the nervous system’s natural healing capacity, it often brings relief where reasoning alone has not.</P2> <H3>Moving towards calm</H3> <P2>EMDR is not about erasing anxiety completely; it’s about helping your body learn that it is safe again. When the nervous system feels calmer, your mind follows. With the right support and a therapist trained in EMDR, you can find new steadiness, confidence and peace in situations that once felt overwhelming. Anxiety no longer has to dictate how you live. Instead, you can move through life with more ease, grounded in a sense of safety that comes from within.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762180774241-CYPH08P5BKWM0LRDXD6S/pexels-pixabay-163255.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="847"><media:title type="plain">EMDR Therapy for Anxiety: Calming the Body When Talking Isn’t Enough</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>When Anxiety Affects the Heart: Understanding Chest Pain That Isn’t Cardiac</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 14:22:52 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/when-anxiety-affects-the-heart-understanding-chest-pain-that-isnt-cardiac</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:690a0bab97ab0477331fa1a8</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>Chest pain is one of the most frightening physical sensations a person can experience. For many people, the first thought is that something serious must be wrong with the heart. After medical checks show that the heart is healthy, there can be relief, but also confusion and frustration. How can chest pain feel so real when the cause is anxiety? Understanding how the body responds to stress can help you make sense of these symptoms and begin to find lasting relief.</P2>

<H3>Why anxiety can cause chest pain</H3> <P2>When we feel threatened or under pressure, the body releases adrenaline and other stress hormones. These prepare us to act quickly, tightening the muscles, speeding the heart rate and changing breathing patterns. If anxiety stays high for too long, this system can misfire, producing sensations that mimic cardiac symptoms. Tightness in the chest, breathlessness, palpitations, tingling in the arms or dizziness can all appear as part of the body’s natural alarm system. They are not dangerous in themselves, but they feel alarming because they resemble signs of a heart problem.</P2> <H3>The cycle that keeps symptoms going</H3> <P2>Many people who experience anxiety-related chest pain find themselves caught in a loop. The physical sensations trigger fear, which increases the body’s adrenaline response, which then intensifies the symptoms. Thoughts such as “something must be wrong with my heart” feed the cycle, keeping the body on alert. Over time, this can lead to avoidance of exercise, social situations or stressful events for fear of triggering symptoms. Therapy helps you break this cycle by calming the body’s stress response and changing how you interpret physical sensations.</P2> <H3>After a clear cardiology assessment</H3> <P2>It is essential to rule out cardiac causes for chest pain, and many people reach therapy after investigations such as ECGs, echocardiograms or stress tests show a healthy heart. At this point, it can help to think of anxiety not as “imaginary illness” but as the body’s protective system becoming overly sensitive. The same biological processes that help us run from danger can, under chronic stress, start firing even when there is no real threat. Understanding this helps shift the focus from fear of damage to learning how to regulate the system.</P2> <H3>How therapy helps</H3> <P2>Therapy offers both physiological and psychological tools for managing these symptoms. In Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT), you learn to recognise the links between thoughts, body sensations and behaviours. For example, noticing how shallow breathing and catastrophic thoughts feed the sense of tightness allows you to interrupt the pattern with calmer breathing and balanced thinking. Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT) helps you focus less on controlling symptoms and more on living fully even when anxiety is present. Compassion-focused therapy supports you to meet your body’s distress with kindness instead of frustration, which itself reduces adrenaline and calms the system.</P2> <H3>Simple techniques that can help right now</H3> <ul> <li><strong>Slow breathing.</strong> Try inhaling gently for four counts, holding for two, and exhaling slowly for six. The longer out-breath activates the body’s calming system.</li> <li><strong>Grounding attention.</strong> Notice five things you can see, four you can touch, three you can hear, two you can smell and one you can taste. This helps move your focus from internal sensations to the external environment.</li> <li><strong>Gentle movement.</strong> Short walks or stretching can discharge built-up adrenaline and signal safety to the body. Avoid complete avoidance of exercise once your doctor has confirmed your heart is healthy.</li> <li><strong>Reassurance through understanding.</strong> Remind yourself, “This feeling is my body’s alarm system, not a sign of harm.” Repeating this helps re-train the brain over time.</li> </ul> <H3>Integrating with medical care</H3> <P2>Psychological therapy works best when integrated with your medical care. Cardiologists and GPs often refer patients for therapy when cardiac causes are excluded, but symptoms persist. This collaboration helps ensure that nothing physical is missed while also addressing the underlying anxiety that keeps the nervous system overactive. Therapy provides the missing piece of recovery, teaching your body to recognise safety again.</P2> <H3>Moving towards calm</H3> <P2>Living with chest pain, even when you know it is anxiety-related, can be exhausting. Therapy offers a structured way to understand what is happening and to restore confidence in your body. Over time, most people notice that as they learn to manage their anxiety, the sensations reduce in intensity and frequency. The goal is not to eliminate all sensations, but to respond to them with calm awareness instead of fear.</P2>

<P2>If you have had a clear cardiac assessment but still experience chest pain, therapy can help you understand and manage these symptoms safely. With the right support, you can regain trust in your body and feel confident that your heart is strong and your mind can be calm.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762266223328-ABWAR1XGVAQFKFGS8IQJ/pexels-freestocks-128597.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">When Anxiety Affects the Heart: Understanding Chest Pain That Isn’t Cardiac</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>EMDR for Health-Related Trauma: When Medical Experiences Leave an Emotional Mark</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 12:18:56 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/emdr-for-health-related-trauma-when-medical-experiences-leave-an-emotional-mark</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:6909edef928d7722ae6acd0e</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>Medical experiences can stay with us long after the physical healing has finished. A sudden diagnosis, time in hospital, invasive procedures or unexpected complications can all leave emotional traces that resurface as anxiety, flashbacks or a feeling of being constantly on alert. Health-related trauma is more common than many people realise. EMDR therapy offers a gentle yet powerful way to help the mind and body process these memories so that they no longer feel overwhelming.</P2>

<H3>When medical care becomes traumatic</H3> <P2>Trauma is not defined by what happened, but by how it affected you. Even experiences that appear routine can be distressing if they involved fear, pain or a sense of powerlessness. Many people describe feeling detached or frozen during treatment, only to find later that sounds, smells or even medical environments trigger panic or nausea. Others notice ongoing anxiety, nightmares or physical tension they cannot explain. EMDR helps the brain and body release these stored responses so that the memories can settle naturally.</P2> <H3>How EMDR supports recovery</H3> <P2>EMDR (Eye Movement Desensitisation and Reprocessing) works by helping the brain reprocess distressing material. During therapy, you are guided to recall aspects of the experience while following bilateral stimulation such as gentle eye movements, tapping or tones. This activates both sides of the brain, allowing the stuck memory to move towards resolution. Over time, the event feels less vivid and the emotional charge reduces. You still remember what happened, but it no longer feels as though it is happening now.</P2> <P2>For health-related trauma, EMDR can be particularly effective because it works with the body’s natural systems. It helps calm the physiological stress response that often remains switched on after medical treatment. People often notice a sense of spaciousness, warmth or release during or after sessions, as if their body has finally recognised that the danger has passed.</P2> <H3>When to consider EMDR</H3> <P2>EMDR may be helpful if you find yourself avoiding hospitals or medical conversations, or if routine appointments trigger anxiety or panic. It can also help if you experience intrusive memories, nightmares, or strong physical reactions such as racing heart, shaking or nausea when thinking about treatment. Sometimes the trauma is not from a single event but from the accumulation of many medical experiences. EMDR can address these layers gently and safely.</P2> <H3>Integrating EMDR with other approaches</H3> <P2>In therapy, EMDR is often combined with elements of CBT, ACT or compassion-focused therapy to help strengthen coping between sessions. CBT tools can support you to manage anxious thoughts day-to-day, ACT encourages acceptance and value-based living even when uncertainty remains, and compassion-focused work helps you respond kindly to your body and mind after everything they have endured. Together, these create a rounded approach to recovery.</P2> <H3>Moving towards peace</H3> <P2>Health-related trauma can leave deep imprints, but it does not have to define how you live now. EMDR offers a path to reconnect with safety and trust in your body. As distressing memories lose their intensity, you can focus again on living, rather than surviving. The goal is not to erase the past but to integrate it, allowing healing to feel complete in both mind and body.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762258748938-L147TSTJ57K3DJYC3RXF/pexels-vidalbalielojrfotografia-1250655.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">EMDR for Health-Related Trauma: When Medical Experiences Leave an Emotional Mark</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Supporting a Loved One Through Cancer: Looking After Them and Yourself</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 14:53:34 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/supporting-a-loved-one-through-cancer-looking-after-them-and-yourself</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:6908c12a65a0631cefb602b7</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>When someone you love is diagnosed with cancer, life can seem to shift in an instant. Conversations that once felt ordinary are suddenly filled with uncertainty, and everyday worries are replaced by bigger, heavier questions. It is common to feel frightened, helpless or unsure what to say. You may want to be strong and supportive, yet also feel anxious, tearful or even angry. Supporting someone with cancer is an act of deep care, but it can also be emotionally demanding. This post explores how to stay connected, offer meaningful support, and look after your own wellbeing at the same time.</P2>

<H3>The shock of diagnosis affects everyone</H3> <P2>Cancer does not only happen to one person. It ripples through families, relationships and friendships. In the first days and weeks after diagnosis, people often describe a sense of disbelief or numbness. You may be trying to take in medical information while also managing your own emotional reactions. It is completely natural to feel overwhelmed. There is no perfect way to respond, and each person in the family may cope differently. Some focus on practical tasks, others want to talk about everything, and some retreat for a while to process what is happening. Recognising and respecting these differences can help avoid misunderstandings at a time when emotions already run high.</P2> <H3>What your loved one might need</H3> <P2>Every person’s experience of cancer is unique. Some want to talk openly about what they are going through, while others need quiet space or normal conversation that does not always revolve around illness. Rather than guessing, it can help to ask directly: “What feels most helpful for you right now?” or “Would you like to talk about it or take a break from it today?” These gentle questions give your loved one permission to express their needs and allow you to adapt as things change.</P2> <P2>Support is not always about having the right words. Often it is about presence, listening without rushing to reassure or fix things. Simply sitting together, making a cup of tea, or doing something ordinary can provide enormous comfort. When someone is facing frightening uncertainty, your calm and consistent presence helps remind them they are not alone.</P2> <H3>Balancing practical and emotional care</H3> <P2>In the early stages of treatment, there may be appointments, medication schedules and changes to routines. Helping with these tasks can be invaluable, but remember that emotional care matters just as much. Encouraging your loved one to rest, eat, and talk about how they are coping can make a real difference. You might gently suggest writing down questions before medical appointments or helping them track symptoms if that feels useful.</P2> <P2>At the same time, it is important not to take on too much. Cancer can create a strong urge to protect or fix things for the person you love, but it is not possible to control the illness or its outcome. Setting realistic expectations about what you can and cannot do will help both of you feel more balanced. Sometimes the kindest thing you can offer is honesty, presence, and care rather than constant action.</P2> <H3>The emotional toll of caring</H3> <P2>Many relatives and partners describe feeling guilty for struggling themselves. You might think, “I’m not the one with cancer, I should be fine.” But your emotional system is under significant pressure too. Watching someone you care about suffer can trigger anxiety, sadness and helplessness. Therapy or support groups for family members can be a safe space to express those feelings and learn coping tools. Even a few sessions can help you understand your stress responses and build resilience for the months ahead.</P2> <P2>Compassion-focused therapy principles can be especially helpful. They encourage you to treat yourself with the same understanding you offer your loved one, recognising that you are also doing your best in an extremely challenging situation. Taking care of yourself is not selfish, it is essential if you want to sustain your support over time.</P2> <H3>When the prognosis is difficult</H3> <P2>Hearing that someone you love may not recover or that treatment options are limited can feel unbearable. People often swing between hope and despair, trying to protect each other from the truth while longing for honesty. There is no single right way to manage these conversations, but open communication tends to help everyone cope better in the long run. If words fail, simply acknowledging, “I don’t know what to say, but I’m here with you,” can be enough.</P2> <P2>Therapy can also help families navigate this stage. It provides a space to think about how to talk together, what to share with children or friends, and how to make time for connection even when things are painful. The goal is not to eliminate sadness but to make space for meaning, love and togetherness in the midst of uncertainty.</P2> <H3>Looking after yourself</H3> <P2>It can feel difficult to prioritise your own wellbeing when someone else is ill, but maintaining small moments of care for yourself will help you stay steady. Try to rest, eat regularly, and maintain supportive social contact beyond the cancer setting. Brief walks, listening to music or time in nature can help calm your nervous system. It may feel strange to enjoy moments of peace, but this does not mean you care any less. It simply means you are allowing yourself to recover between emotional demands.</P2> <H3>Holding on to connection</H3> <P2>Even in the most difficult circumstances, connection can be healing. Whether through quiet companionship, shared humour, or honest conversations, maintaining closeness can bring strength to both of you. Remember that your presence is enough, and that caring for someone you love includes caring for yourself too. Support, compassion and balance are what sustain both people through the uncertainty of illness.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762181521892-FC2MZHQ7Z88CSBFCJX8R/pexels-thirdman-7659552.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">Supporting a Loved One Through Cancer: Looking After Them and Yourself</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Practical, evidence-based strategies to help manage anxiety</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 14:37:21 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/practical-evidence-based-strategies-to-help-manage-anxiety</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:6908bd29ad9f442e54867896</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>We all feel anxious at times. It’s part of being human. Anxiety is the body’s way of preparing us to deal with potential threats, sharpening our focus and readiness to act. But when that alarm system stays switched on, even when there’s no real danger, it can start to take over daily life. Many people describe living with anxiety as being constantly on alert, their minds racing, hearts pounding, and sleep disturbed. This post explores what happens when anxiety becomes overwhelming, and how therapy can help you find steadiness again.</P2>

<H3>What anxiety really is</H3> <P2>Anxiety is not a sign of weakness or failure. It is a protective system that has gone into overdrive. When we face a stressful situation, our brain sends signals to the body to release adrenaline and cortisol. These hormones prepare us to take action, speeding up the heart and tightening the muscles. In short bursts, this system helps us perform well. But if it remains active for too long, the constant physiological tension can leave us feeling exhausted, irritable, and trapped in a cycle of worry.</P2> <P2>People often find their anxious thoughts sound convincing. “What if something terrible happens?” or “I’ll never cope with this.” Over time, these thoughts start to feel like facts, even when they are not. Therapy helps by slowing down this process so you can observe the patterns with more perspective and less judgment.</P2> <H3>Understanding the cycle of anxiety</H3> <P2>Most people experience anxiety as a loop that links thoughts, feelings, physical sensations, and behaviour. For example, you might have a thought such as, “What if I make a mistake at work?” That thought triggers a wave of tension, perhaps a fluttering stomach or racing heartbeat. To manage those feelings, you might avoid tasks or over-prepare. Avoidance can bring short-term relief, but it reinforces the belief that you cannot cope. Therapy helps to break this cycle gently and gradually so that confidence can return.</P2> <H3>How therapy helps</H3> <P2>There is no single approach that fits everyone. In therapy, the aim is to understand your unique version of anxiety and tailor strategies to meet your needs. Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) helps you identify and challenge unhelpful patterns in thoughts and behaviour. Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT) builds the ability to hold anxiety lightly, focusing on actions that align with your values rather than on eliminating anxious feelings. Compassion-focused therapy strengthens the part of you that can respond with kindness and reassurance instead of self-criticism. Cognitive Analytic Therapy (CAT) looks at repeating patterns from past relationships that might still be shaping how you respond to stress today. Each of these approaches offers a different doorway to understanding yourself and regaining balance.</P2> <P2>Therapy is also a space where you can feel understood rather than judged. Many people discover that naming anxiety aloud helps loosen its grip. The process of exploring your experience with a therapist can itself bring relief, as you begin to see how anxiety developed and what keeps it going. Gradually, you learn to relate to yourself and your thoughts in a new way.</P2> <H3>Practical steps to ease anxiety day to day</H3> <P2>Alongside therapy, there are small, evidence-based techniques that can make a real difference in managing anxiety symptoms. These include:</P2> <ul> <li><strong>Grounding in the present moment.</strong> When anxiety takes over, focus on your senses. Notice five things you can see, four you can touch, three you can hear, two you can smell, and one you can taste. This brings the mind back from “what if” thinking to the here and now.</li> <li><strong>Breathing to calm the body.</strong> Slow, steady breathing helps regulate the nervous system. Try breathing in for four counts, holding for two, and exhaling for six. The longer out-breath signals to your body that it is safe to relax.</li> <li><strong>Reconnecting with values.</strong> Anxiety can narrow your world. Ask yourself, “What matters to me, even with this anxiety present?” Taking small steps towards those values—whether that’s spending time with loved ones, going for a walk, or completing a task—builds confidence and restores meaning.</li> <li><strong>Practising self-compassion.</strong> Notice how you speak to yourself when anxious. Would you say those words to a friend? Try offering yourself the same warmth and patience you would give someone else who is struggling.</li> </ul> <H3>When to seek help</H3> <P2>If anxiety is stopping you from living the life you want, or if you find yourself avoiding situations, struggling to sleep, or feeling constantly tense, professional help can be transformative. Therapy offers a structured way to understand what is happening and to develop skills that last beyond the sessions themselves. It is not about removing anxiety entirely but learning to live well alongside it. Many people find that, over time, the sensations and worries lose their intensity, allowing room for calm and confidence to grow.</P2> <H3>Moving forward</H3> <P2>Therapy at our practice begins with an open conversation about what you have been experiencing and what you hope to change. Together we explore what might be maintaining your anxiety and choose a therapeutic approach that feels right for you. Over time, you learn practical tools for managing anxious thoughts and sensations, while building compassion and flexibility in how you respond to them. The goal is not perfection, but freedom - the ability to live a full life even when anxiety occasionally shows up.</P2> <P2>If you are ready to explore therapy for anxiety, you can reach out for an initial session. You do not have to face this alone. With understanding, gentle structure, and evidence-based techniques, it is possible to move from feeling trapped in anxiety to living with greater peace and purpose.</P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1762180475566-7ZWQ5KA94FO4LQM1SHAF/pexels-latronico-776855.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1125"><media:title type="plain">Practical, evidence-based strategies to help manage anxiety</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Start Your Mental Health Journey This World Mental Health Day</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/start-your-mental-health-journey-this-world-mental-health-day</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:68e80b1e25f92613da11eceb</guid><description><![CDATA[<P2>Every year on 10 October, World Mental Health Day invites us to reflect on how we look after our inner life, our thoughts, feelings, resilience and connections. What if this year, instead of seeing it just as an awareness day, you used it as a launch point, a day to begin or recommit to your own mental health journey?</P2>

<P2>“Journey” is a fitting word. Mental health is not a destination or a fixed state, but something we move through and tend to over time. Some days will feel harder, some lighter, but each step matters. If you are reading this, maybe today is your signal to begin. And if you are further along, it might be time to deepen or refresh your path.</P2>

<H3> Today is the first day of  your mental health journey</H3>



<ul> <li><strong>It is never too late or too early.</strong> Whether you have struggled for years or only recently noticed something is off, you can begin from where you are.</li> <li><strong>You get to define what “journey” means for you.</strong> It might include therapy, self-reflection, small daily habits, group support or creative expression. It does not have to be dramatic to be meaningful.</li> </ul>



<H3>How to mark this day meaningfully</H3>

<P2>Here are gentle, evidence-informed ways to begin or renew your journey. You can pick one or more that resonate with you:</P2>

<ul> <li><strong>Pause and reflect:</strong> Spend 5–10 minutes writing or thinking about this prompt: “What would I like my mental health to look like in six months’ time?”</li> <li><strong>Choose one micro habit:</strong> a short breathing exercise, a daily walk, saying “no” to something unhelpful, or a gratitude check each night. Consistency matters more than intensity.</li> <li><strong>Reach out:</strong> Tell someone you trust, a friend, family member or colleague, that you are focusing on your mental health. There is power in connection.</li> <li><strong>Learn a tool:</strong> Try a simple grounding, mindfulness or self-compassion exercise, for example, noticing three things you can see, hear or feel right now.</li> <li><strong>Seek professional support:</strong> If you have recognised ongoing distress, therapy or counselling can offer tailored help. Taking that first step is brave and a meaningful commitment to yourself.</li> </ul> <H3>Why therapy can help your journey</H3>

<P2>Therapy offers more than fixing problems. It builds skills, awareness and self-compassion. In this practice, we draw on approaches such as CBT, ACT, compassion-focused work and Cognitive Analytic Therapy. Here is how they can support your journey:</P2>

<ul> <li><strong>CBT and ACT</strong> help you understand and shift patterns of thinking and behaviour that may be holding you back.</li> <li><strong>Compassion-focused therapy</strong> nurtures kindness towards yourself when uncertainty, self-criticism or shame emerge.</li> <li><strong>Cognitive Analytic Therapy</strong> helps you trace relational patterns, how you relate to others and yourself, and rewrite unhelpful cycles.</li> </ul>

<P2>When therapy is part of a broader journey, alongside daily practices, self-reflection and social support, it becomes anchored in your life, not something separate or exceptional.</P2>


<H3>Inviting you: a short World Mental Health Day ritual</H3>

<P2>You might like to use this small ritual today, or adapt it:</P2>

<ul> <li>Sit quietly for a minute or two and breathe.</li> <li>Think of one intention you want to carry forward, for example, “cultivate self-kindness”, “seek help when overwhelmed” or “notice small acts of joy”.</li> <li>Write it on a small card, or set a note or reminder.</li> <li>Tell yourself, “Today is the first day of my journey,” and imagine one small step you will take this week in support of that intention.</li> </ul>

<P2>World Mental Health Day is more than observance, it can be a turning point. If you are thinking of therapy, or want to explore a direction, give us a call. </P2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1760038130637-LM2EE4JF2UTF32RX80WQ/unsplash-image-fzqxoFJytiE.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="938"><media:title type="plain">Start Your Mental Health Journey This World Mental Health Day</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Simple Grounding Techniques for Anxiety</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 11:17:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/simple-grounding-techniques-for-anxiety</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:68d1968c256f0d05ba706164</guid><description><![CDATA[<h3>What Are Grounding Techniques?</h3>
<p2>When anxiety strikes, it can feel overwhelming. Racing thoughts, a pounding heart, or a sense of panic can take over. Grounding techniques are simple tools that bring your attention back to the present moment. They help calm the nervous system and give you a sense of control.</p2>

<p2>These techniques can be used anywhere – at home, at work, or when out and about. Over time, practising grounding regularly can make anxious moments easier to manage.</p2>

<h3>Why Grounding Helps</h3>
<p2>Anxiety often pulls us into “what if” thinking about the future. Grounding interrupts this cycle by focusing attention on the here and now. It shifts your mind away from worry and towards what your senses can notice in the present. This can help reduce the intensity of anxious feelings and make them pass more quickly.</p2>

<h3>Five Simple Grounding Techniques</h3>
<p2>Here are some practical strategies you can try next time you feel anxious:</p2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>5-4-3-2-1 Method:</strong> Name five things you can see, four things you can touch, three things you can hear, two things you can smell, and one thing you can taste.</li>
  <li><strong>Deep Breathing:</strong> Breathe in slowly for four counts, hold for four, and breathe out for six. Repeat several times.</li>
  <li><strong>Cold Water Splash:</strong> Run cold water over your hands or splash your face to bring your focus back to your body.</li>
  <li><strong>Describe Your Surroundings:</strong> Out loud or silently, describe the colours, shapes, and textures around you.</li>
  <li><strong>Hold an Object:</strong> Keep a smooth stone, keyring, or small item in your pocket. Focus on how it feels in your hand when you’re anxious.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Using Movement as Grounding</h3>
<p2>Gentle movement can also help anchor you when anxiety rises. Walking slowly, stretching, or pressing your feet firmly into the ground can bring awareness back to the body. Some people find that naming each step as they walk (“left, right, left”) can be particularly calming.</p2>

<h3>Making Grounding Part of Daily Life</h3>
<p2>Grounding techniques work best when they become familiar. Try practising them when you are calm so they feel easier to use during stressful times. You could build them into your daily routine, such as taking a few grounding breaths before a meeting or while commuting.</p2>

<h3>When to Seek Support</h3>
<p2>Grounding is a helpful tool, but it may not be enough if anxiety feels overwhelming or constant. If you find that anxious thoughts are affecting your sleep, work, or relationships, talking to a psychologist can make a big difference. Therapy can help you explore the root causes of anxiety and develop a wider set of coping strategies.</p2>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>
<p2>Grounding techniques are simple, practical tools that you can use anywhere to manage anxiety. They bring your focus back to the present and help reduce feelings of panic or overwhelm. Practised regularly, they can be a reliable way to feel calmer and more in control of your mind and body.</p2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1758566060229-3LMEPB3FKGDE0URL36NL/pexels-noellegracephotos-906097.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">Simple Grounding Techniques for Anxiety</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Understanding the Differences: Clinical Psychologist, Counsellor, Psychiatrist, Therapist…</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 11:03:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/understanding-the-differences-clinical-psychologist-counsellor-psychiatrist-therapist</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:68dedc0a303c4e2b17e94210</guid><description><![CDATA[<p2>When people decide to look for professional help with their mental health, one of the first challenges can be working out who to approach. You might see terms like counsellor, clinical psychologist, psychiatrist, or therapist, and wonder what the differences are. This post explains these roles in clear, respectful language so you can make an informed choice about what kind of support feels right for you.</p2>

<h3>What Does a Clinical Psychologist Do?</h3>
<p2>A clinical psychologist is a highly trained mental health professional who usually holds a doctorate-level qualification (DClinPsy) and is registered with the Health and Care Professions Council (HCPC). Clinical psychologists are trained to assess, diagnose and treat a wide range of emotional and psychological difficulties, from anxiety and depression to complex trauma and physical health-related challenges. They do not prescribe medication, but they use evidence-based therapies such as Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT), Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT), Eye Movement Desensitisation and Reprocessing (EMDR), and Compassion Focused Therapy (CFT). In private practice, a clinical psychologist may offer therapy to individuals, couples, or families, tailored to each client’s needs.</p2>

<h3>What About Counsellors?</h3>
<p2>Counsellors are trained to provide a safe, confidential space to explore difficulties, usually in the here-and-now. Training routes can vary, from diploma to degree level, and many counsellors are registered with organisations such as the British Association for Counselling and Psychotherapy (BACP) or the National Counselling and Psychotherapy Society (NCPS). Counselling often focuses on talking through challenges, relationships, or feelings, and many people find it an accessible and supportive way to work through life’s struggles. Some counsellors also undertake additional training in specific therapeutic approaches. While a clinical psychologist is trained in multiple therapy models and psychological assessments, counsellors often specialise in providing consistent, empathic support that helps people process experiences and emotions.</p2>

<h3>What Does a Psychiatrist Do?</h3>
<p2>A psychiatrist is a medical doctor who has specialised in mental health. Psychiatrists are able to prescribe medication for conditions such as depression, bipolar disorder, or psychosis. They often work in NHS hospitals, community services, or private clinics. In some cases, psychiatrists also provide talking therapy, but their main role is usually to diagnose and manage mental health difficulties from a medical perspective. For people with more severe or complex conditions, or when medication is an important part of treatment, seeing a psychiatrist can be essential. Psychologists and counsellors may work alongside psychiatrists as part of a wider care team.</p2>

<h3>Is “Therapist” Just Another Word?</h3>
<p2>The word “therapist” is an umbrella term that can describe many professionals who offer therapeutic support, including counsellors, psychologists, psychotherapists, and even some nurses or social workers with therapy training. This can be confusing, because “therapist” itself is not a protected title. It’s always worth asking about someone’s background, training, and registration, so you know who you are working with and what to expect. You may see listings for therapists of different kinds, and choosing the right one depends on whether you want psychological therapy, counselling support, or medical input.</p2>

<h3>How Do I Choose the Right Professional?</h3>
<p2>There is no one-size-fits-all answer, but here are a few helpful pointers:</p2>
<ul>
  <li>If you want <strong>evidence-based psychological therapy</strong> for anxiety, depression, trauma, or complex issues, a <strong>clinical psychologist</strong> may be a good fit.</li>
  <li>If you are looking for a <strong>safe space to talk through personal or relational difficulties</strong>, a <strong>counsellor</strong> may be right for you.</li>
  <li>If you think you might need <strong>medication alongside therapy</strong>, or if your difficulties feel severe and medical in nature, you may wish to see a <strong>psychiatrist</strong>.</li>
  <li>If you’re not sure, we are always happy to have a chat and tell you what kind of professional we would recommend. If you are having conversations directly, we would recommend asking about their training, and exploring what feels comfortable for you.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Respecting Different Paths</h3>
<p2>Each profession brings its own strengths, and all share a commitment to helping people feel better. Some clients see more than one professional over time, or combine approaches. The important thing is finding someone you feel safe with, who has the right training to support your needs. Whether you work with a counsellor, clinical psychologist, or psychiatrist, seeking help is an important and brave step towards feeling more grounded and well.</p2>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>
<p2>The language around mental health support can be confusing, but understanding the differences between these professions can hopefully help you take that next step. You will find many options available. If you are unsure, you are welcome to reach out and ask questions. The most important part of therapy is not just the title of the professional you see, but the sense of trust, understanding, and collaboration you build together.</p2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1759436169325-VJW44Y00CI8ITDYQ3HMQ/pexels-cottonbro-4101143.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">Understanding the Differences: Clinical Psychologist, Counsellor, Psychiatrist, Therapist…</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>An Introduction to Compassion Focused Therapy</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 20:03:55 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/an-introduction-to-compassion-focused-therapy</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:68ded8647a73895772df92c0</guid><description><![CDATA[Compassion Focused Therapy was developed in the UK by Professor Paul 
Gilbert. It combines ideas from psychology, neuroscience, and mindfulness 
to support people who experience high levels of self-criticism or shame.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p2>Many people come to therapy saying they feel harsh with themselves, constantly self-critical, or stuck in cycles of shame. While other people may see them as capable and kind, their own inner voice can feel relentless. Compassion Focused Therapy (CFT) is a powerful approach that helps to quieten that critic and build a kinder, more balanced relationship with yourself. If you’ve been wondering what compassion focused therapy involves and whether it could help, this post offers an introduction.</p2>

  


  
    
<h3>What is Compassion Focused Therapy?</h3>
<p2>Compassion Focused Therapy was developed in the UK by Professor Paul Gilbert. It combines ideas from psychology, neuroscience, and mindfulness to support people who experience high levels of self-criticism or shame. At the heart of CFT is the idea that our brains have three key emotion systems: the <em>threat system</em> (linked to fear and self-criticism), the <em>drive system</em> (linked to achievement and striving), and the <em>soothing system</em> (linked to calm and care). For many people struggling with their mental health, the threat system is on overdrive, and the soothing system feels under-developed. CFT helps strengthen that soothing system, so you can feel safer and more supported internally.</p2>

<h3>Why Self-Compassion Matters</h3>
<p2>It is easy to believe that self-criticism will make us perform better or avoid mistakes. In reality, research shows that excessive self-criticism increases anxiety and depression, and makes it harder to recover from setbacks. By contrast, self-compassion gives us the emotional resilience to try, fail, and learn without collapsing into shame. CFT is especially relevant if you often feel “never good enough”, experience perfectionism, or find it difficult to accept kindness from others. Therapy provides a safe space to explore these feelings and practise treating yourself with the same understanding you might naturally show to someone you love.</p2>

<h3>How Does Compassion Focused Therapy Work?</h3>
<p2>In therapy sessions, your psychologist or therapist will help you understand how your patterns of shame and self-criticism developed, often rooted in early life experiences. Together, you will practise “compassionate mind training”, which may include:</p2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Breathing exercises</strong> that help settle the body and signal safety.</li>
  <li><strong>Imagery practices</strong>, such as imagining a compassionate figure who can offer warmth and reassurance.</li>
  <li><strong>Compassionate letter writing</strong> to yourself, reframing harsh self-talk into supportive words.</li>
  <li><strong>Behavioural experiments</strong> such as small acts of kindness towards yourself in daily life.</li>
</ul>
<p2>These practices help your brain and body experience what it feels like to be cared for, both by others and by yourself. Over time, people often report feeling less dominated by the inner critic and more able to meet life’s challenges with balance and courage.</p2>

<h3>Who Can Benefit From CFT?</h3>
<p2>CFT is often helpful for people who live with anxiety, depression, trauma, eating difficulties, or perfectionism. It can also be particularly useful if you recognise that shame or self-criticism play a big part in your struggles. Sometimes people choose compassion focused therapy when they notice that other approaches, like purely cognitive or problem-solving therapies, don’t fully address their self-critical inner voice. CFT can be used on its own or integrated with other evidence-based approaches such as CBT or ACT, depending on your needs.</p2>

<h3>Simple Practices You Can Try Now</h3>
<p2>You don’t need to wait until therapy begins to start building a more compassionate mindset. Here are a few simple practices you can explore:</p2>
<ul>
  <li>Place a hand gently on your chest or shoulder as a small reminder of warmth and safety.</li>
  <li>Take slow, steady breaths, focusing on an exhale that is slightly longer than your inhale.</li>
  <li>Write down one thing each day that you appreciate about yourself, however small.</li>
  <li>When your inner critic appears, pause and ask: “Would I speak this way to someone I care about?”</li>
</ul>
<p2>While these are small steps, they begin to shift the balance between harshness and kindness inside.</p2>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>
<p2>Living with constant self-criticism or shame is exhausting, and often people believe they just have to “try harder” to silence it. Compassion Focused Therapy shows that there is another way: learning to approach yourself with warmth, patience, and care. This is not about being indulgent or avoiding responsibility, but about creating the emotional safety you need to grow and thrive. If you are looking for face-to-face therapy (in Tunbridge Wells, Tonbridge or other areas within Kent) or online, and recognise yourself in these patterns, CFT may be a supportive option to explore. Reaching out for help can feel daunting, but it can also be the first step towards a more balanced and compassionate life.</p2>]]></content:encoded><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1759435390912-IMPK3ZT6P4T3K4RDJDCD/pexels-shvetsa-4672712.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="2250"><media:title type="plain">An Introduction to Compassion Focused Therapy</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Managing Stress at Work: Practical Strategies That Help</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/managing-stress-at-work-practical-strategies-that-help</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:68d196bc0802672cbe78fbd9</guid><description><![CDATA[Learning how to manage stress in the workplace is an important step in 
protecting your wellbeing.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Why Work Stress is So Common</h3>
<p2>Most people experience stress at work from time to time. Deadlines, meetings, and heavy workloads can quickly build up. Over time, constant stress can affect both mental and physical health, leading to fatigue, irritability, and difficulty concentrating. Learning how to manage stress in the workplace is an important step in protecting your wellbeing.</p2>

<h3>Spotting the Signs of Work Stress</h3>
<p2>Work stress shows up in different ways. Being able to recognise the signs early can help you take action before things feel overwhelming.</p2>

<ul>
  <li>Feeling tense, anxious, or irritable during the day.</li>
  <li>Trouble sleeping or switching off after work.</li>
  <li>Headaches, muscle tension, or stomach problems.</li>
  <li>Difficulty focusing or making decisions.</li>
  <li>Lack of motivation or job satisfaction.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Practical Strategies for Managing Stress at Work</h3>
<p2>There are small, everyday steps that can help reduce stress and build resilience. These strategies may seem simple, but they can make a big difference when practised regularly.</p2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Take breaks:</strong> Short pauses during the day help your mind reset and reduce pressure.</li>
  <li><strong>Prioritise tasks:</strong> Make a list and focus on the most important jobs first.</li>
  <li><strong>Set boundaries:</strong> Try to finish work at a set time and avoid checking emails late at night.</li>
  <li><strong>Move your body:</strong> A short walk, stretch, or climbing the stairs can ease tension and refresh focus.</li>
  <li><strong>Use calming techniques:</strong> Breathing exercises, mindfulness, or grounding techniques can reduce stress in the moment.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Creating a Healthier Work Environment</h3>
<p2>Sometimes stress comes from the way we set up our workspaces and routines. Small changes can make work feel more manageable.</p2>

<ul>
  <li>Keep your desk organised to reduce distractions.</li>
  <li>Personalise your workspace with calming items, like photos or plants.</li>
  <li>Adjust your chair, screen, and lighting to avoid physical strain.</li>
  <li>Drink enough water and avoid too much caffeine, which can increase tension.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Talking About Stress at Work</h3>
<p2>It can feel difficult to speak up about stress, but sharing your concerns often helps. Talking with a manager, colleague, or HR team can lead to practical changes. Many workplaces also offer support programmes, such as employee assistance schemes, that can provide confidential help.</p2>

<h3>When to Seek Extra Support</h3>
<p2>If work stress feels constant and is affecting your health, relationships, or sense of wellbeing, it may be time to seek professional support. A psychologist can help you explore coping strategies, build resilience, and manage the impact of stress more effectively.</p2>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>
<p2>Stress at work is common, but it doesn’t have to control your life. By noticing the signs early, making small daily changes, and reaching out for support when needed, you can protect your mental health and create a more balanced working life.</p2>]]></content:encoded><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1758566106291-9MLHVTPOZC08O67QSL4Q/pexels-energepic-com-27411-313690.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1125"><media:title type="plain">Managing Stress at Work: Practical Strategies That Help</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>The Link Between Exercise and Mental Health</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/the-link-between-exercise-and-mental-health-fBWNN</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:68d1965bfd53143fefb8e49f</guid><description><![CDATA[<h3>Why Exercise Matters for Mental Health</h3>
<p2>Exercise is not only good for the body – it is also one of the most effective ways to support your mind. Research consistently shows that physical activity can reduce symptoms of stress, anxiety, and depression. It also boosts energy and improves overall wellbeing.</p2>

<p2>You don’t need to spend hours in the gym to feel the benefits. Even short bursts of movement can make a real difference to how you feel day-to-day.</p2>

<h3>How Exercise Helps the Brain</h3>
<p2>Exercise affects the brain in several positive ways:</p2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Releases endorphins:</strong> These “feel-good” chemicals help lift mood and reduce stress.</li>
  <li><strong>Improves sleep:</strong> Regular movement helps regulate sleep cycles, making it easier to rest at night.</li>
  <li><strong>Reduces tension:</strong> Physical activity can release built-up muscle tension linked to stress.</li>
  <li><strong>Boosts focus:</strong> Exercise increases blood flow to the brain, supporting concentration and memory.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Types of Exercise That Support Mental Health</h3>
<p2>You don’t need to follow a strict routine or take up intense training to benefit. Choose activities you enjoy, as this makes it easier to stick with them.</p2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Walking:</strong> Gentle, low-impact, and easy to fit into daily life. Walking in green spaces adds extra calming effects.</li>
  <li><strong>Yoga:</strong> Combines movement with breathing and mindfulness, making it ideal for stress relief.</li>
  <li><strong>Running:</strong> A natural mood booster that helps release endorphins and build resilience.</li>
  <li><strong>Team sports:</strong> Add a social element, reducing feelings of isolation.</li>
  <li><strong>Dancing:</strong> Fun, uplifting, and a great way to combine movement with music.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Making Exercise Part of Daily Life</h3>
<p2>One of the biggest challenges is finding time and motivation. Small, manageable changes often work best. Try to look for opportunities to move more in your everyday routine.</p2>

<ul>
  <li>Take the stairs instead of the lift.</li>
  <li>Walk or cycle short journeys instead of driving.</li>
  <li>Set a timer to stand and stretch every hour at work.</li>
  <li>Join a class or group to stay motivated and accountable.</li>
  <li>Start small – even 10 minutes of activity can improve your mood.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Exercise and Stress Management</h3>
<p2>When you feel stressed, exercise can be a healthy outlet. It helps shift your focus away from worries and gives your body a way to release pent-up energy. Many people find that a walk, run, or yoga session helps them return to challenges with a clearer perspective.</p2>

<h3>When Exercise Alone Isn’t Enough</h3>
<p2>While exercise can be a powerful tool for mental health, it isn’t a cure-all. If you are experiencing ongoing anxiety, low mood, or loss of motivation, you may benefit from additional support. A psychologist can help you explore what’s happening and build a personalised plan that includes both lifestyle changes and psychological strategies.</p2>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>
<p2>Exercise is one of the simplest, most accessible ways to support mental health. Whether it’s a daily walk, a yoga class, or dancing in your living room, movement can lift your mood and build resilience. Start small, choose activities you enjoy, and notice how even small changes can improve your sense of wellbeing.</p2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1758566012245-S5EV8EMRSXJOLW3IEWFE/pexels-noellegracephotos-906097.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">The Link Between Exercise and Mental Health</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>Coping with Sunday Night Anxiety</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 11:10:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/coping-with-sunday-night-anxiety</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:68d1962431f2694a28f14167</guid><description><![CDATA[<h3>What is Sunday Night Anxiety?</h3>
<p2>Many people notice a rise in stress or worry on Sunday evenings. This “Sunday night anxiety” often shows up as racing thoughts, trouble relaxing, or a feeling of dread about the week ahead. It can make it difficult to sleep and set a negative tone for Monday morning.</p2>

<p2>While occasional nerves are normal, regular Sunday night anxiety can take a toll on your wellbeing. The good news is that there are simple strategies to make Sundays calmer and more enjoyable.</p2>

<h3>Why It Happens</h3>
<p2>Sunday night anxiety is usually linked to anticipation. The weekend is ending, and thoughts about work, school, or responsibilities begin to surface. Common triggers include:</p2>

<ul>
  <li>A heavy workload waiting on Monday morning.</li>
  <li>Upcoming meetings, deadlines, or exams.</li>
  <li>Feeling unprepared or behind with tasks.</li>
  <li>General worries about balancing work and personal life.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Practical Ways to Ease Sunday Night Stress</h3>
<p2>There are steps you can take during the weekend to reduce anxiety and start the week on a stronger footing.</p2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Plan ahead:</strong> Spend a short time on Friday afternoon or Sunday morning making a simple to-do list for the week. This helps reduce uncertainty.</li>
  <li><strong>Limit screen time:</strong> Avoid checking work emails late on Sunday, as this can trigger stress before the week even begins.</li>
  <li><strong>Prepare for Monday:</strong> Lay out clothes, pack bags, or prep meals so you feel organised.</li>
  <li><strong>Schedule something pleasant:</strong> Plan a small enjoyable activity on Monday, such as a coffee with a friend, to balance work demands.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Create a Relaxing Sunday Evening Routine</h3>
<p2>Shifting the focus away from work and towards rest can make Sunday evenings more enjoyable. Try to create a routine that helps you wind down.</p2>

<ul>
  <li>Cook a favourite meal or enjoy a warm drink.</li>
  <li>Take a walk outdoors to release tension.</li>
  <li>Do a short meditation, breathing exercise, or gentle yoga stretch.</li>
  <li>Read, listen to music, or watch something light-hearted.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Build Healthy Sleep Habits</h3>
<p2>Sunday night anxiety often interferes with sleep. To give yourself the best chance of a restful night:</p2>

<ul>
  <li>Keep a consistent bedtime, even at weekends.</li>
  <li>Avoid caffeine late in the day.</li>
  <li>Switch off screens an hour before bed.</li>
  <li>Try writing down worries or tasks to “park” them for the night.</li>
</ul>

<h3>When to Seek Extra Support</h3>
<p2>If you feel anxiety has become overwhelming or spreading into the rest of the week, it may be helpful to speak to a psychologist and explore the causes and find coping strategies to bring down the anxiety levels.</p2>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>
<p2>Anxiety that peaks the night before the working week is very common, but it doesn’t have to control your weekend. With planning, relaxation, and healthier routines, you can ease the transition into the week. Over time, these changes can help you approach Mondays with more calm and confidence.</p2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1758565961735-HT6M1ZSRENERC8W8COKD/pexels-cottonbro-3944464.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">Coping with Sunday Night Anxiety</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>The Power of Routine: How Daily Structure Supports Mental Health</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 20:08:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/the-power-of-routine-how-daily-structure-supports-mental-health</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:68d18f5e4316bf49dd061595</guid><description><![CDATA[<h3>Why Routines Matter for Mental Health</h3>
<p2>At times we might think of routines as dull or restrictive, but in reality they can be an anchor for our wellbeing. Having a predictable structure to the day reduces stress, improves sleep, and gives us a sense of control. For people struggling with anxiety or low mood, even small daily rituals can make life feel more manageable.</p2>

<h3>The Science Behind Structure</h3>
<p2>Our brains like predictability. When we know what is coming next, our nervous system feels calmer. This is why children thrive on routine, and the same applies to adults. Research has shown that regular daily habits can:</p2>
<ul>
  <li>Improve sleep quality by regulating the body’s natural rhythms</li>
  <li>Reduce stress by creating predictability</li>
  <li>Boost productivity and focus</li>
  <li>Support healthier eating and exercise patterns</li>
</ul>

<h3>Simple Routines to Try</h3>
<p2>You don’t need to overhaul your entire lifestyle to feel the benefits. Start small and build gradually. Here are some ideas you could try:</p2>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Morning routine:</strong> Wake up at the same time each day, stretch, drink water, and take a few deep breaths before looking at your phone.</li>
  <li><strong>Workday rhythm:</strong> Schedule regular breaks away from screens. Even five minutes to stand up and move can boost focus.</li>
  <li><strong>Evening wind-down:</strong> Switch off devices an hour before bed, dim the lights, and read or listen to calming music.</li>
  <li><strong>Weekly rituals:</strong> Plan a walk in nature, a meal with loved ones, or time for a hobby you enjoy.</li>
</ul>

<h3>When Life Feels Overwhelming</h3>
<p2>It’s easy to slip out of routine when life feels chaotic. During times of stress, structure becomes even more important. It gives us stability when everything else feels uncertain. If you’re finding it hard to keep a routine, start with one or two anchor points, such as a set wake-up time and a daily meal at the table.</p2>

<h3>Balancing Flexibility and Structure</h3>
<p2>Some people worry that routine means rigidity. In fact, the best routines leave room for flexibility. Life is unpredictable, so it’s helpful to think of routine as a framework, not a strict timetable. For example, you might plan a daily walk but leave the exact time open, depending on weather and energy levels.</p2>

<h3>Routines and Mental Health Recovery</h3>
<p2>For those recovering from depression, anxiety, or trauma, routines can be a vital part of healing. They help rebuild confidence, create purpose, and encourage self-care. Small daily goals, such as making the bed or going outside for five minutes, can gradually restore a sense of achievement and control.</p2>

<h3>Practical Tips to Get Started</h3>
<p2>If you’d like to bring more routine into your life, try the following:</p2>
<ul>
  <li>Pick one area of your day that feels chaotic and create a simple habit around it.</li>
  <li>Use reminders on your phone or notes around the house.</li>
  <li>Celebrate small wins and notice how you feel after sticking to a habit.</li>
  <li>Be patient – routines take time to build and will naturally evolve.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>
<p2>Routines are not about perfection or living the same day over and over. They are about creating rhythm, predictability, and a sense of safety. By making small changes, you can build a structure that supports your mental health and gives you more energy for the things that matter most.</p2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1758565710135-X1WYMENL6V8SBYK9N291/nathan-dumlao-r-KfktlyBL0-unsplash.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="640" height="427"><media:title type="plain">The Power of Routine: How Daily Structure Supports Mental Health</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>The Benefits of Mindful Walking for Mental Health</title><dc:creator>Rachel Whatmough</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 11:06:25 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.thetunbridgewellspsychologist.co.uk/blog/the-benefits-of-mindful-walking-for-mental-health</link><guid isPermaLink="false">651bd580535fd6545ccb670b:651be432fa912564fda8aef8:68d195b55a42e017ac3d82c8</guid><description><![CDATA[<h3>What is Mindful Walking?</h3>
<p2>Mindful walking is a simple practice that combines gentle movement with focused attention. It involves paying close attention to the act of walking itself – the feeling of your feet touching the ground, the rhythm of your breath, and the sights and sounds around you. Unlike a brisk walk for exercise, mindful walking is about slowing down and being fully present.</p2>

<h3>Why Mindful Walking Helps</h3>
<p2>Modern life is full of distractions. Many of us spend our days rushing from one thing to the next, rarely pausing to notice what is happening in the moment. Mindful walking offers an opportunity to step out of that cycle. By walking with awareness, you give your mind a rest from constant planning, problem-solving, and screen time.</p2>

<p2>Research shows that mindfulness practices can reduce stress, improve mood, and help manage anxiety. Walking in itself already brings physical benefits, but adding mindfulness strengthens the mental health effects.</p2>

<h3>How to Practise Mindful Walking</h3>
<p2>You don’t need special equipment or a long stretch of time to begin. A few minutes of mindful walking can make a noticeable difference. Here are some steps to get started:</p2>

<ul>
  <li>Choose a quiet place – a garden, park, or even a hallway indoors.</li>
  <li>Stand still for a moment and take a few deep breaths before you begin walking.</li>
  <li>Walk slowly, paying attention to each step.</li>
  <li>Notice the sensation of your feet lifting and touching the ground.</li>
  <li>Bring your awareness to your surroundings – sounds, smells, colours.</li>
  <li>If your mind wanders, gently bring it back to the feeling of walking.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Everyday Opportunities for Mindful Walking</h3>
<p2>You don’t need to set aside a special time every day. There are many ways to build mindful walking into your routine:</p2>

<ul>
  <li>On your way to the shops, slow down and notice your surroundings.</li>
  <li>Use part of your lunch break to walk outside mindfully.</li>
  <li>Walk between rooms at home with awareness instead of rushing.</li>
  <li>Turn a dog walk into a chance for mindfulness, noticing how your pet explores the world.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Mindful Walking in Nature</h3>
<p2>Walking outdoors can make mindfulness even more powerful. Nature offers soothing sights, sounds, and scents that help calm the nervous system. Being in green spaces has been shown to reduce stress hormones and improve overall wellbeing. If possible, try mindful walking in a park, woodland, or along the coast. Even a few minutes surrounded by nature can boost your mood.</p2>

<h3>Making it a Habit</h3>
<p2>Like any new practice, mindful walking can feel unusual at first. It helps to start small and build gradually. Aim for just five minutes at a time and increase as it becomes more natural. Some people find it useful to set a reminder on their phone, while others link the practice to an existing routine, such as walking to the car or to the train station.</p2>

<h3>When to Seek Extra Support</h3>
<p2>Mindful walking can be a valuable tool for managing everyday stress and mild anxiety. However, if you find that your worries, low mood, or feelings of tension are becoming overwhelming, it may help to talk to a professional. A psychologist can work with you to build coping strategies tailored to your individual needs.</p2>

<h3>Final Thoughts</h3>
<p2>Mindful walking is a gentle and accessible way to improve your mental health. By slowing down and paying attention to your steps, you can bring calm, clarity, and balance into your daily life. It requires no equipment, costs nothing, and can be done almost anywhere. A few mindful steps each day may be all it takes to begin feeling more grounded and at ease.</p2>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/651bd580535fd6545ccb670b/1758565859612-C2TVVJDZ5VIGN4C8N9N5/pexels-luisdelrio-15286.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1000"><media:title type="plain">The Benefits of Mindful Walking for Mental Health</media:title></media:content></item></channel></rss>